Hello?
Yeah.
Hello.
Go ahead and introduce you and-
In fact, it's Elie who is speaking first.
Hmm?
Elie speaks first. We have merged the talks.
Oh, okay.
So yeah.
Oh, no, that's it.
Yeah, I know.
Okay.
Welcome, everyone, to the
May the Data Be Structured session.
I think I'll leave the introduction of yourself up to you.
I'm bad with pronouncing names, but...
Yeah. Okay. Welcome to the section
32,
May the Data Be Structured.
I'm Adeline Carné, your moderator, and my co-moderator
is Wouter Coe there.
He's the keeper of the time, so have a look
to stay on time.
I will thank--
Well, it's already in the presentation, but I
have to thank the sponsors, and I don't know how I can...
So let me know that.
I'm lost.
Just thank the sponsor.
Yeah. Thanks to the sponsor. You should have the name,
but it's Friday. You should remember them.
I hope my voice is not too difficult for you today.
And the first talk
is not only mine, in fact, so Elie Saliba will begin,
and I will finish it.
So let's go.
So hello, everybody. The first talk of this morning is going to
explore a little bit the history of one of TDWG's
standards, which is called the SDD.
The SDD was developed in the context of identification keys.
So in case you're not very familiar,
historically, the main style of identification key is simple access
identification keys.
They can be available on paper or online.
The oldest one is attributed to a French guy called Lamarck in
1815, and it basically works on the principle of yes and
no question at every step.
However, the limits of the simple access identification keys
are that it's very difficult to formulate doubt,
and to be able to go back and forth in the system.
Their creation and update can take a lot of time.
It usually falls on the shoulders of taxonomists to do so.
And it's very possible or likely to get stuck if you depend on
characters that are not visible on the specimens you are trying to identify
at a certain time, like forever having missing the flower on a plant or
the fruit.
Free access identification keys, which are mostly available in
digital format, but not only,
offer a different approach.
There's not one path, but a multiple of different decision trees that basically
you recreate a simple access key every time you use this,
but the description needs to be formalized.
It's possible to formulate doubt, and you can add to it additional help and
resources, taking advantage of the digital format.
It's possible to introduce weight to the different characters without forcing paths
to influence the users, without limiting them to a
single type of access.
So
as I just said, it's possible to generate simple access keys based on structured
description data. There are multiple modules that were developed, especially in the
early 2000s, to do so.
And these algorithms, they rely on
input data consistent on description and taxa,
descriptions of taxa, descriptions of the specimen, or even sometimes rules.
So depending on what you are trying to do, you might have a different way of
structuring this data, and
so in some cases you will have the classical approach for
taxonomy, which is the description of taxa, but you can also describe
specimen and basically do an identification level at the individual level.
Delta was one of the first formats that was
used and that was developed in
the 1980s.
Delta stands for Description Language for Taxonomy.
It
was validated by TADWIG in the '80s.
It's considered currently as externally maintained, and it's still maintained to a
certain extent. And we owe this to Michael Dalwitz
in Australia,
who developed and maintained
this standard since the earliest 1970s.
So all that we are presenting today are not exactly very new things.
This is even older than TADWIG as it exists as an organization.
But a lot of issues were associated
with Delta. First,
it depended a lot on the software that was also developed by the
Australians at that time. And
so
what happened is that other application of free access keys developed their own
formats to be able to exchange
or store data. And the problem is, thus because of the association of
Delta with its eponymous software, SDD was introduced in the hope
that it would help interoperability.
So SDD or structured
description data,
the idea of it was to be able to exchange keys in
between different
softwares that were developed in different parts of the world.
So
SDD was developed first and the
discussion around it started at the 1998 meetings, thanks to the guy
figured here, Gregor Hagedorn, who did his PhD on the
subject, a fairly long 400 pages on
the question.
And at the time, we didn't have access to Zoom and a
lot of other things, so most of the meetings were face-to-face, a little bit
around the world, so you can appreciate how much budget they had at the time.
And SDD XML schema reached its version 1.0
and was approved as an international standard in 2005 at the
Saint Petersburg TADWIG.
GBIF then got into the game and asked for new developments,
which led to 2006 and 2007, the release of an
SDD 1.1 version, and this constituted the last update
of that standard for the public.
SDD was then used in multiple European projects such as VIBRENT and
EDIT.
And
sadly,
most of the information linked to the development of that standard was put on a
wiki page
that was lost. So
to prepare this presentation and to prepare the history of
SDD, we had with Adeline to rely on printed
archives that were present
at the personal archives of the people who were there at the time.
And so
there is still a GitHub that you can access under TADWIG control, where you can
find a little bit of the information about that original standard, but
it really needs curation because it was just everything they found, they put it
there. So it's not really structured, which is kind of ironic considering the
context.
However, we still have a chance that a lot of the people who were there at the time
are still here and can tell us orally what happened and how
everything was developed at the time.
So SDD itself, and we're going to go more into technical details later,
had five main objects or five main classes that are of interest.
They describe entities that are sometimes called items.
The descriptors, the descriptor states, the description themself, and groups, which
permit the agglomeration of these entities.
It's written in XML, which was pretty much standard at the
time, and it's a little bit technically difficult to understand because it's
not very for human beings easy to read.
The flexibility that it provided at the time-- So SDD lets you do a little bit of
your own thing, but basically that played a role against its main
objective of being interoperable.
And so
it
thus created a new problem to align things in between different standards.
AI was not part of the process at the time.
Metadata is poorly captured because it wasn't really the discussion in
2005. And user choices and paths are not saved at all.
This particular point is going to be talked about a little bit later.
And that's for the first part of this presentation.
The second part is going to be given by my colleague, Adeline.
Yeah.
So now we know everything about the history of SDD.
The idea is to give you an example
with one software, with Expert.
So
Expert is a system to manage the descriptive data.
It's quite old. The first version has been developed in the
'80s. It was a standalone software.
Then we've got Expert 2 with exactly the same--
We are very close, just new update technology.
And then you've got Expert 3, the online version.
So
the current version, it's Expert 3,
it's online, it's free,
and you can have some collaborative works, and it's still
compatible with the SDD.
If we have a look with the different
change, the evolution of the Expert,
you can see everything evolve. The storage begin with four
files with a main file in XML
and different imported export.
Very soon after the ratification of SDD, you've got-
Import and export in Expert 2, and now in Expert 3,
it's continue. We changed the identification part.
At the beginning, it was a Java applet, and now
we use web services. And to use them, you need
to import an SDD.
And so
quickly,
this is an Expert 2 file before the
SDD, and then an SDD in Expert 2.
They are quite similar.
And most of
the work was to map because
the structure of the model was very close and
it's not
just something that happened.
In fact, the Expert 2 teams was in the
discussion of the SDD,
so it makes sense.
And very quickly,
Lucide, so another system to manage descriptive data and Expert
implementing the SDD.
And a comparison has been done in
2008.
Yep.
I'll go quick.
And even in that time, so
2008 at the TED week, the two SDD were not fully
interoperable. Such a pity. And it was
not a problem with
values, with the tags, but the way
the XML has been structured
and written. So
we can do something, I think.
Very quickly, just to show you, SDD is
everywhere in Expert 3 workflow. So yeah,
everywhere.
Yeah, so
we've got the five main concept Eli
already
show you. So the descriptor can--
I'm sorry. It's difficult today. It's Friday.
Yeah. You've got a lot of descriptors, with different information you
can add to them.
The state, it's all the value that one descriptor
can
have.
The
described entities, so in Expert, it's item, but it can be
taxa or specimen or scopes or a lot of things like that.
The description themself. So
each item is described with one or several state from
each descriptors. The group you can manage and filter,
and you have additional information.
Most of the time
it's to illustrate.
And we can find everything in Expert
with the main objects.
And there are some example of specific thing
in the SDD and Expert.
So
you can have different type of descriptor.
You can have different information about taxa
and stuff like that.
Well, SDD is a huge standard.
They're seeing more or less of everything and more you can imagine.
So I've put there some example of thing that
exist in SDD, but not in Expert for the moment,
with some example. For example, in Expert,
the descriptor are only one string
of characters, but you can cut them into an entity and
a quality in the SDD.
You've got a lot of additional information that have
been solved
and not in SDD. In fact, glossary, you can add
some definition
in Expert, but they are
whispered in the whole file.
And sometime
we've got some challenge.
We try to maintain and reuse the SDD structure, but we need to
specialize its meaning. So there's two example.
Measure exist in SDD, and we add different type for them.
And rating exist in SDD, and
we use them for observation convenience, and we
choose a scale between one and five.
So we preserve the structural compatibility, but
maybe it will be difficult for the semantical part.
And another example are the calculated descriptors that doesn't
exist in SDD. The idea is to generate some
description with some descriptors that
already exist, but
adding a
logical expression
to automatically
updating them.
And we choose to convert them as categorical descriptors.
So
the state is frozen. That's a pity.
We lost some information with that.
And yeah, Expert is not finished. We
continue. We are working hard on the first
version,
and there are a lot of thing
we are working on.
Some are in SDD and will be implement now.
So maybe needs to be in SDD.
We really want to preserve something open, shareable, and
interoperable,
but not only for expert, for everyone.
So maybe expert four
is the best opportunity to restart the discussion with
everyone who want around the SDD.
So
if you have any question or comment, do not hesitate.
Are there any questions from the audience
right now?
I have a
question, if I can.
Yeah.
Some of these SDD things,
they seem kind of hacky,
the way that you have to implement them for
SDD to do what you want.
How easy do you think it would be to get it into the SDD standard?
Because it's been quite dormant
for a while.
I'm not sure I understand.
Do you have some help?
So if I understand well your question, it's considering
how the standard has been dormant for a while-
Yeah
... how difficult it is to re-implement things in a correct
way or, yeah.
Yeah.
Well, one of the things with that standard is that it's been pretty well thought,
and as I mentioned in my presentation, Gregor Hagdorn wrote his whole PhD,
a good chunk of his PhD was about the standards.
We have very good documentation in a way of what it
was meant to be. It's an old
conversation that trace back to the 1990s with Régine
Vins and Jacques Lebbe thesis on the subject, too, so we have a lot of elements
that we can get even there. The issue with SDD is that it
was, in many ways, a bit early.
Mm.
So it was
thought to be able to implement stuff that did not appear in the different
softwares until quite later.
Mm.
And so,
there is probably a lot of things that needs to be redone,
because now we know what happened in the next 20 years, and we know
what we actually need, what
worked and what didn't work, what was never really implemented.
And so to a certain extent, it's a bit easier to go back now and say, "Okay, this
is working," or, "We have a good hope that this is going to work, so we
can probably adapt SDD to be able to take care of this." And all of that thing
never really worked. We never really found a nice way to implement it in any
software. So maybe we should just put this aside and not bother with it.
So the conversation itself, we have a good soil, a good
something to be able to grow something out of it.
But yes, the challenge is that we've lost a good chunk of the archives, which
raised a lot of questions inside of TADWIG to make sure that this
never happens again, that we lose archives and discussions like this.
But
as a technical discussion, I don't think it's that difficult to
open back the
discussion on SDD.
Thank you. I think that's the time we have.
Yeah.
So, we're onto the next speaker, and I'm-
And it's you
... I hope I pronounce this correctly, but it's me.
Yep.
So, let's see.
That's it.
All right.
I cannot see my own slides, but I made them, so I should be able to
remember this.
I'm going to be talking more about the implementation of keys
and in the age of AI, how we can combine the two and
how keys and AI can complement each other,
rather than make each other obsolete.
I want to start out with this by saying
identifications are the base of most of the
data that we work with. Oh, yeah.
Every map we have, every dot means that
someone took a decision of what something was.
So,
this is quite essential.
If you don't have an identification, you're not going to get the rest of the
observation, and that's all of the data that we work with.
So I've been working on this for a couple of years
now.
Oh, nice. None of my pictures work.
I work with
species identification app in the form of
image recognition.
It's called Artodactyl. There is supposed to be a beautiful screenshot over there.
You can look it up. It's free. It's in English.
It's no user, no sign up. No nothing.
And that's been the thing that we've done since the start, that we keep it low
threshold, and we focus on showing the
uncertainty to the user,
so that anyone can use this.
And when you take a picture of something like a mushroom, it will tell you
that please don't eat anything based on AI, because that's a very bad idea.
I'm hoping people nowadays know that.
But when we launched this app, AI was still very new.
It was before ChatGPT and stuff like that.
However, not everything can be done with image
recognition. There's certain
things you have to look at that you will not get from a picture.
There's an educational aspect that you're missing when you're just getting a
list of species and that's it.
So, yeah.
So we've made an interface.
I'm going to see if I can open this in a browser because Adobe
sucks.
Yeah, that looks better.
Where are we? There we are.
I'm sorry about this.
F11 work?
Control F?
Oh.
I'm just going to do it like this. I think this is the best experience I can
get for you guys right now.
So there's the app.
That's so stupid. I can summarize it with Copilot, but fullscreen
is not an option somehow. So, that tells you about the times we're
living in.
So there's the app.
That's what I mentioned about the mushrooms warning people, very important,
but it's not enough to just have this
app telling you, "Here's a list." So we need the keys as
well, and I've, over the past year, been working with experts that
put their knowledge into these keys.
It's a lot of work, both for them and for me,
but it works really nicely. You get these keys as described, where you don't
have a book where if you don't know the answer to question five,
you're stuck, and you're going to have to either guess or give up.
With these digital keys, you have multi-axis, so you can choose the questions that
you answer and take it from there.
And I've been working with the format of Claves, but
nowadays, certainly with AI,
mapping one standard to another
is becoming more trivial. So I think that the focus on the standard
doesn't have to be as heavy as before.
And once you have these two
elements, you have the AI and you have the keys, you can
start doing really cool stuff. This is one pipeline that I
have been working on where the user takes a picture,
sends it to the robot, which will come with a number of
species candidates. We can take that list of
species as a filter on such a key because it is
so multi-axis
and present the user with a key for these three species
only, and by answering two or three
questions that are very specific to these
species, they can find out what it is and learn a lot in
the process. And I think that's a really
great opportunity
for these technologies to talk together.
So I've made a working demo. You can check it out here if you want.
Even if you didn't bring your own dragonfly pictures today, I have a link
so you can get some,
and it will basically do what I just said.
You can identify any species. It talks to the normal API,
but if there's one or more dragonflies in there,
it will tell you that, "Hey, I have a key on dragonflies.
Do you want to go there and use these species to
identify what it is using the key?"
So if you do that, you're sent to a screen like this,
and some of the options have already been eliminated because none of the
species are that size.
So you're helped a lot along the way, and there's a lot less room
for user error as well, which is a big problem within these keys because they're
big and they're difficult.
Another cool thing that you can do that I've been working on,
it's not scalable right now, but it shows some of the
potential for AI in the future.
User comes with a picture, sends it to the CNN,
the image recognition, and it comes with a list of species again.
This time, we don't just give a key to the user, we give it to a
multimodal
VLM,
together with the original picture.
And we ask it to look at the things that we know to be true of
all of these species.
And we don't give it the answers. We ask it to
look at the picture and tell me which of these characters can you
see. And that means that we, with a language
model, can generate an explanation of why you're looking at what
you're looking at. So it will
determine that it can see blue wings in a picture, and we know that to be true
for all of these species. So it can tell you, "Yeah, it's one of these three
species because I can see that it has blue wings. It has white legs.
It has a dorsal stripe there.
And what you can't see, but what I know to be true about these
species, is that the anal appendages are
shaped like this." So you can really make an explanation that is
way more educational than what an AI just
recognizing a picture can do.
However, this does require that we have these keys, and it's a lot of work,
and we're never going to get all of these keys, and a lot of them already exist,
but they exist in these books that
are hard to come by, and they're hard to read.
And they are very linear. You have that problem where if
you're stuck, you're stuck, and you're not going to find out what it is.
So what we've been working on is
an agentic pipeline where we can feed it
some literature, in this case, mammal books of Norwegian mammals,
and we can
tell the agent to extract all of the facts it
can find
about the, in this case, rodents that we're interested in.
So it will go into the sources. It will not use its own knowledge.
It will
only get things from the sources and extract things
like the size of the ears, the length of the tail, whatever you need to know to
identify these rodents. With this, we can collate them again
into a key.
Not only a key that we're digitizing, but maybe a key that didn't even exist
before because all of the information was hidden in these descriptions.
I've given a talk on this on Tuesday, if you want to have a look.
I think it's recorded.
But the point is that this makes it feasible to
have these keys at scale now, because doing
this with experts directly, it takes them days to weeks at
minimum to digitize this. And I wish I had the
funding to have them do that. I would
like it much better if I could have the experts do this than AI, but it's
not scalable. It's not going to happen.
And with these AIs, we can have a draft key.
It's not perfect, but it works.
If it's one source, it's under $10.
If it's multiple sources like this one, I think it was about $30.
I made a rough calculation.
And that means that we can have
a very different role for these experts because they now can review
a working key in the right format through an
interface, where previously we would just give them an empty Excel
sheet and tell them, "Yeah, go make a key." And
that's a steep learning curve for them.
They're learning stuff that is not their field of expertise, that is not
maybe their interest.
And we find that using AI in this manner, we can
bypass a lot of that friction.
So I want to, again, end
the talk with saying that these identification keys
and AI,
some people have said, "Why do we even need identification keys now that we have
AI? Because
it's going to solve everything, right?"
And I very much want to highlight that we need the domain knowledge
for the educational part, for the grounding of the AI
itself.
And AI will be fine.
The bubble will burst, but there will still be people working with AI and making
cool stuff.
They're not going to disappear. These experts are,
well,
I won't say they're disappearing, but they're certainly retiring
to a great degree, and
we're not making any new ones. Every new biologist has to be an
ecologist, and we don't
make enough taxonomists. So we need to take care that we
save this kind of information.
Again, if you want to know more about the pipeline and how we digitize these keys,
you can have a look at the
symposium from Tuesday. So
with that, I haven't seen any notes, but I guess my time is up.
Yep, it is up.
So if there are any questions.
Okay.
I will do my own running.
Wouter, thanks very much.
Can you talk about the maturity of the Clavis JSON format?
For example, if I make a JSON API off of our software,
could I be using your key interface right now just by sending that
JSON out and giving you the right endpoint?
Yeah, absolutely. It's
a peer-reviewed format. I
hesitate to call it a standard because a standard is really a standard when people
treat it as a standard.
As expert, it's a
more limited scope than SDD,
because SDD really can represent a key verbatim as it was
published. Clavis does not do that.
It tears keys apart and
puts them back together.
But yeah, I
have yet to meet an expert with a key that has
something in their key that they cannot represent within Clavis.
And
as I said, I think the format is getting more trivial, and I
was happy to see yesterday that Pensoft has now
implemented Clavis as one of the formats that they can import and
export to
for a publication.
So your phone app, if you
can give
me the different seed guidance, like if you give it one for TaxonWorks-
Yeah
... would that work out of the box, or is there other config around there as
well?
I'm not familiar enough with TaxonWorks. What does it give me?
If you give me Clavis.
Uh-huh.
Pretend I can do Clavis.
Oh, yeah.
And you just give me a different URL.
It's just raw Clavis, there's no other-
Oh, yeah.
In this API as well, well, there is no API.
It's just a URL to a Clavis file, and it gets the
JSON file, and it works from that. So the player is there, the editor is there.
Please use it.
Yeah.
Cool.
Oh, there's a
Hey, thank you. Very cool talk. So I always thought that those taxon keys
work that way, that if you miss one question, you sort of miss it because that's
how they have to work, because how that taxonomy identification works.
So how do you work around that? How do you solve this?
Yeah.
The key
very basically works in a way that it will ask you questions
that it knows the answer to for all remaining species.
But there can be multiple things that separate
the same set of species. So it may be that we
know the size of all of them, then we can start asking about the size, because
is it
below four centimeters or above? But they also may
have
the leg coloration for the same species.
And then you can, if you just have a picture and it's hard to estimate the
size, but you can see the legs, you can answer that one.
And maybe then implicitly, well, everything that has white legs is
also a smaller species, so you will never have to answer that question.
At any point, and we try to
get our experts to work in this way, to put in
more than you would need for the classical key and to break their
things apart.
So don't say that this is a small species with white legs and
blue wings and this and that and that, which they like to do, that
they give almost a species description, and you just have to pick the right one.
We really find that the users find it
easier to evaluate
one characteristic at a time, and then we can illustrate it well,
like
this is what a leg looks like, and this is what it looks like when it's white, and
this is what it looks like when it's black.
So that's how it works in a nutshell. Yeah.
Oh.
I'm going to continue until I'm told not to.
So you mentioned the cost. Is that with a frontier-like model, and
B, are you starting to train RAG train or augment train,
Gwens or 27Bs or?
Thank you. Yeah. This is a frontier model.
It's Claude Opus in this case, so not frontier, frontier, but
pretty much frontier.
So in my estimation, this is the maximal cost because I
think that's overkill,
but I wanted to prove that it can be done.
And yeah, my next step is very much to get a Gwen
model or maybe one of the new ones where they just have a
deterministic-
Jeff.
Jeff. Yeah.
I think it came out after I came to Oslo here, so I've been
dying to try that, too. There's new models coming every week, and you
can do
cool new stuff.
But I think even with the frontier model, and I want to point out it
is heavily subsidized by the tech bros, but
it does work, and it is feasible in terms of costs as well.
And even if the cost would be tenfold,
I think it would still be feasible.
So
if you have $300 for a key, an
expert is not going to
usually do it for that kind of price. So, yeah.
I think we can streamline this a lot, but...
Still good?
Good.
Okay.
Yeah. Looking good.
Yeah? Good.
No more questions?
Maybe during the discussion time.
Yeah. We have discussion time as well.
Notes this time.
Good.
The next speaker, Beyond Traditional Identification Keys: An Example of
Hybrid Identification Method using Deep Learning and Expert3Keys for Insect
Identification, which is a virtual talk by Agathe Puisson.
Yeah?
I hope the
video part works as well as the-- Well, better than the...
So hi, thank you for coming to my talk.
So today I will be presenting an example of a hybrid
identification method using both deep learning
and interactive keys such as Expert3Keys
for insect identification. So a project that was
supported by the ECOPLUS project at Sorbonne
University.
So first, museum collections are a real treasure trove of data
that contain large amounts of data accumulated in the form
of specimens.
And this is really interesting because
there is a great precision in the taxonomy and the
identifications of those different specimens.
But this also allows us to capture a wide diversity of both
species and morphological variations that is present
in both collections.
And the collection data is increasingly made available in different
forms. So, for example, in
2D digitization,
which are photographs of specimens, but also
more recently in 3D scans that are made
available.
So the question that we are asking here is how can we effectively harness this
wealth of data, and what opportunities does it offer to improve
our understanding of biodiversity?
And so in this project, I was particularly interested in a
real pillar of biology, which is
taxonomic identification using
all of this data.
So we usually identify a taxon
from specimens by describing its different morphological
and color characteristics. And so traditionally, this has
been done by using
identification keys, where you describe the presence or absence
of a morphological character. And more recently, there has been
the development of interactive identification keys,
where the user can interactively
answer those presence or absence of characters.
Not one character at a time, but several characters at a time, reducing the
need for precise expertise and
the need for time for species
identification.
So even more recently, we have seen the development of automated identification
by using deep learning method, where you input some kind
of data from your specimen, and then it automatically
outputs a possible species identification.
So we have put two widely known ones.
So the first one is BirdNET for bird songs, and second one is a
PlantNET for plants images.
And so those methods are
less precise, usually in term of
taxonomic identification than the expert-based keys.
And they require a lot of training data
to work.
So here I was really interested in the opportunity to combine the precision
of identification keys with the automation power
of deep learning. And so my goal here was to develop hybrid
methods to get the best of both worlds.
So the idea is to input an image or photograph of
your specimen
in a deep learning model trained on the photographs of
collection specimens.
So the pros are, as I said, that you capture a wide range of
morphological variation, and you have precise identification,
meaning that you can control the quality of your database.
But those kind of ecological datasets are often small
compared to those typically used in deep learning and with a high
number of classes. So for example, high number of species.
And also there is a lot of imbalance in classes.
So
we often have a lot of data for one species and a few data for
another.
The goal will be to output the most probable taxon list that could
be then used to pre-filter the
interactive identification keys,
and to let the user have control over the final
decision on the species identification.
And so for this, I used
deep learning methods based on the supervised contrastive learning, and
more specifically, the SepCon method,
that are method that are specialized to learn similarity between
images.
So the way that this kind of method works
is based on pairs of positive images.
Positive meaning that they come from the same class, and so they are supposed to be
similar, such as the two number one on the left.
And pairs of negative images that come from different classes.
And so all of those images will go through a same
convolutional neural network, which are neural network that are specialized to
analyze image data.
And those network outputs a representation of the images in a reduced
dimensional space. So those are the representation vector
that are on the right of my slide.
And the way that the neural network learn is by
modifying its weight, so that representation vectors from
positive images are pulled together
in the representation space, and representation vector from
negative pairs are pushed apart.
And so in this way, we can learn the morphological discriminative features of
images that make them similar or dissimilar.
So I applied this method on a dataset of
French ladybirds, for which we already had an identification key
ready.
And I obtained images
of specimens from the Natural History Museum collection in
Paris for most of the same taxa.
The way I evaluated my model was by using a measure called the hit rate,
which means the success rate among the 10 nearest
neighbors. So meaning that for one image, you
get the 10 most probable taxon list, and if the right species
or the right taxon is in it, then the hit rate is one, and
if it's not, it's a zero.
And so we evaluate the performance using the average across all photograph.
So for example, if we have a hit rate of 80%, it means that the correct taxon is
found among the 10 nearest neighbor in 80% of the cases.
So after training, I obtained this embedding space where the
different phenotypic groups are clearly
separated and clustered together.
So I did a hyperparameter search by getting the model with
the highest hit rates on my validation data.
And so I won't get into the details, but
basically the selected model was a deep
network that could capture complex features that
had long training and moderate data augmentation.
So I gathered two different validation datasets to
evaluate the performance on external, previously unseen data.
So the first one I gathered from images from GBIF,
that is not standardized at all. So there is a lot of variation in both
lighting and pose. And the second one was much more
standardized. It's from a professional photography website.
And so I could see the performance on two kinds of
standardization levels.
And so I got a hit rate of about 90% for both of
the dataset, meaning that my model was able to generalize well
to external data.
So then we implemented
this model in Expertree by building this
little interface where the user can
input an image,
and then the
identification keys is automatically filtered based on the output of
the deep learning model. So here, for example, we have an example with a
Wikipedia illustration of the seven dot ladybirds, and as you can see, the
right species is in the filtered results.
But when we tested it, we saw that there was some kind of limitation when the
background was
too dark or too complex, and in general, when it's too different from our
training data set where the background was removed.
And so this is a limitation of the model.
And then I quantified again in a path length to the correct
identification, meaning that I counted the steps needed
in the ID key to get to the correct ID.
And so you can see that on the left you have without AI pre-filtering,
and on the right you have with AI pre-filtering.
And so we go from an average of 4.2 to one point steps
on average.
And interestingly, so the longer the path was without
AI filtering, the greater the reduction is after our AI
filtering. So the more complex cases of identifications are
greatly reduced by using AI pre-filtering,
meaning that we have less probability to make a
mistake during the
identification process.
So as a conclusion,
using the great wealth of data from museum
collections,
we combined the automation and flexibility of deep learning with
the explainability and precision of identification keys.
And this could lead to the reduce of the need for expertise
and the generalization to external data that could
be really useful, for example, in cases of the use of those ID keys
in a large-scale biodiversity monitoring, where the people
that are using those keys are rarely experts on the
specific taxa that are studied.
And as a perspective, we could now evaluate the increase in the
percentage of correct ID made by humans with and without AI,
because so I did a
theoretical quantification of
the gain
made by filtering with AI, but now we could test it with real humans.
Adding an automatic background removal step would
probably improve performance. And
lastly, I would be very interested in applying
this AI pre-filtering to other taxa for which we have an
identification key to see how well
this training workflow generalizes to other
taxa.
So yeah, thanks
you for your attention, and I'd like to thank again the ECOPLUS project
and my collaborators, so Sylvain Boucaud, Romain Latier, and Régine Vineuil-Neb
from Sorbonne University and the Muséum national d'Histoire naturelle.
Thanks.
Okay, so
we are a little late, and I don't know if Agathe is online,
but Régine is online, so maybe we
can go to the next virtual talk,
and if we've got question at the end during the discussion
part, maybe Régine will be back.
Vine from Sorbonne University in Paris.
This presentation was-
Yep. So
next talk, another virtual
ones,
about what we are
going to do with the identification
process.
Yep.
Good morning, everybody. I'm Régine Vine from Sorbonne
University in Paris. This presentation was prepared with
several colleagues. Two are present with you in
Oslo if you would like to discuss further,
Adeline Kerner and Elise Saliba.
So what is the topic of this talk? We are
particularly interested in the data generated during the use
of identification tools.
Our main questions is quite simple: Can we
use an exchange standard such as SDD, not
only to share identification keys, but also to record and
share the way these keys are used?
Identification tool based on morphological data
have changed considerably over time,
from
identification of specimen with single access key,
where
the user follow a predefined sequence of questions,
then interactive free access key,
which provide more flexibility. The user can choose which character
to examine next, depending on what can be observed on the
specimen.
More recently, automatic
AI identification tools based on images or sounds.
And now, I read identifications,
as explained just before by Agathe Puissant.
So today, there are several ways of
identifying an organism, and consequently several
types of information that can be generated during the
identification process.
And identification tools are also used in many different
contexts: research, education and training,
citizen science program, activities with general public,
and so on.
In all these situations, the final
identification is interesting, but the
process that led to the identification can
also be very informative.
Let me give you a concrete example coming
from SPipole. SPipole is a French citizen science
program developed by the
National History Museum in Paris.
In this citizen program, participants
photograph insects visiting flowers, identifying
them with a free access key,
and then submit their identification and their picture
to the SPipole.
The Expert 3 development team implemented a system
to record the identification pathways followed
by participants.
This made it possible to analyze the sequence of character
choice, identify errors, collect feedback, and
generate metrics
such as the number of character used and/or the frequency of
backtracking.
So the identification session itself contains valuable
information.
But the limitation in this example with SPipole
was that we record the
identification session in a specific closed format.
And this raised the question, how could we share
such information using an open standard?
So what is to store and to share to analyze identification
sessions?
In case of a single access
key,
it can be represented as a graph, and when a user follows such a
key, the identification trajectory is a path through
that graph.
So one could say, if SDD can represent a
single access key, perhaps it can also represent
a path.
But is an identification session really
only a path through a graph?
The answer is clearly no. And this is the
central
point of our proposing.
An identification session is more than a path.
We need to know, for example, who performed the identification and what
specimen was being identified.
We may also want to record the observations made by the user,
and the user can express uncertainty,
correct
backtracking, also to modify previous response.
And in hybrid identification process, part of the
identifications may come from AI assistance.
So the identification
session is a combination of context, observation,
and navigation through an identification process.
What cover the current SDD standard?
SDD was designed to represent descriptive data and also single
access key, as presented here.
So
SDD already provides a way to represent the graph of an
identification key, and we are not proposing to replace
the existing representation of key.
Rather, we are asking whether SDD can be
extended so that this exchange format can also
describe what happens when the key is used.
So if current SDD doesn't support identification
sessions,
it has to be adapted, and we propose to extend
SDD to represent
a context, for example, the user, the specimen, the date of
identification,
the identification trajectory, including the question asked, the
response given, uncertainty, correction, backtracking.
And third, in the case of hybrid identification, information
about the AI component, for example, the model
used and its output.
But here we will not define all these aspects.
To extend SDD,
we could suggest to add three objects:
identification context, identification session, and
identification process. And for today's presentation, we
just focus on the identification session.
An identification session,
we propose to represent it as a sequence of steps.
A step can be a question, a response, or a result.
For example, we can start with the question
Q1, the user response
R1, the identification process produce a
result, and so on, and it's possible to have backtrack
So a step can be
a question, a response, and a result.
And a response,
in case of qualitative question, a response may contain one state or
several possible states together with a confidence value.
For quantitative question, the response may be a numerical value or
interval or another expression together with
information about accuracy.
The important point here
is that we should not lose the uncertainty expressed by the observer
when the session is stored.
The terms confidence, accuracy, and compatibility, of course, will
need precise semantics in a future standard.
A step can also be a result,
and a result leads to three possible outcomes: a new
questions, a end, meaning that the identification
process terminates,
or in case of backtrack, it leads to a previous question,
typically to modify a previous response.
And when the
result is end, the identification may
produce one or several taxa together with information such
as compatibility or probability.
But end does not necessarily mean that a successful identification has been
obtained. It simply means that the identification process
has terminated.
Let me illustrate the complete process with a simple example here,
with the first questions, a first result, a second
question two, a second result, and then a
backtrack to question one to modify the answer and
then obtain as result an end. It means the name of a
species X.
The important thing is that the sessions record the complete trajectory,
and this complete trajectory is not a simple path in
a key.
For analyzing the use of identification tools, that
information can be extremely valuable, as we have seen with
SPLE example.
So far, we have mainly considered a human interacting with an
identification key, but the same approach should also
accommodate hybrid identification.
In that case, what should we store about the AI component?
At minimum, we may need a reference to the trained AI
model and its output. For example, the output
could be a list of taxa associated with probability,
as in the Agathe Puissant example.
So what for a next future?
Our next step
is to implement a new identification service linked with Expert
4, which is the new version of Expert currently under development.
Our objective is to continue to offer
different identification services,
one for generating single access key, one to offer free access key,
but also the possibility of hybrid identification, and
importantly, the possibility of storing and sharing
identification sessions.
So we would explore how an
extended SDD standard could help maintain such open
system where identification data and identification
processes can be exchanged, analyzed, and
reused.
So to conclude, identification tools generate
valuable session data.
Current SDD represent identification keys, but not the
full identification session.
We propose extending SDD to represent context, process,
uncertainty, backtracking, and eventually hybrid
identification.
This shared identification session could also provide valuable
data set for training and evaluating AI models,
because they contain not only the final identification but also the
observation, uncertainty, and reasoning
pathway that led to it.
The identification key define the graph.
The identification session record the trajectory
to obtain the identification.
So we look forward an extended exchange
format, SDD,
in order that identification session become accessible and
reusable data.
Thank you for your attention.
Okay, so Regine is online, so if you have any
question, do not hesitate.
No one, so maybe we can continue
with the last talk.
So now
we are dealing with bioacoustic data with
Cyprien Pokorski.
Okay.
It's okay.
So hi, everyone. I'm Cyprien Pokorski from Reunion Island
University.
And the slide here.
From Reunion Island University, and I'm here to present you
one part of my works on my PhD thesis,
and present you the iterative signal-based system
framework we developed to try to characterize
and classify the cetacean vocalization.
Why we need to classify the cetacean vocalization?
It's because
in bioacoustics, especially marine bioacoustics, we'll
use a lot of passive acoustics monitoring,
which means we do a hydrophone in the water and wait for
signal, and sometimes whales.
And we can directly observe whales by
this approach.
For example, minke whales can be detected around
100 or more kilometers away from the hydrophone,
and we have
full-time recording.
In this recording, we have sometime one event, sometime more,
an hour or there's
sometimes weeks of recordings.
It can be difficult to detect and to try to classify and
very chronophageous
to be done.
Also,
in the literature,
a lot of people use neural network, actually.
Some bioacousticians use that because it works,
it's functional. But they lost
all the information of why the vocalization is
classified here,
why they evolved
in time and geographically.
It's
the main question to make interpretability in the
classification
in this works.
For example, you can see a recording of a
minke whale.
Depends on people and their annotators, people can see
one, three, five different vocalization in
this spectrogram.
So
it's very difficult, and they have no
international consensus on how to describe that
and how to classify.
To answer this question,
we developed a framework, ISBS. It's a
hybrid framework
with neuronal and symbolic AI,
and try to use the better of each one
to do that.
Decomposed in three way. First one, the detection,
because I say it's really chronophageous to do
that with a lot of PAM data,
and
no more internship to do that.
Second way, the description.
We try to not
classify directly the raw data
because a lot of data. For example, the spectrogram
just before
was million
or maybe more prints. So
very difficult and
a lot of data
to classify to work with them.
So the second part is the description part.
We try to reduce to some descriptors, and
these descriptor can characterize
the vocalization.
And the last part is a classification
way. Use ICABS, was
developed in our laboratories 20 years ago.
And at the beginning, used to classify
species, coral species and turtles
species. We adapt this to
try to classify
cetacean vocalization.
I will develop each part. First of all,
detection.
As I say, chronophageous.
Two way to do that. First one,
manually.
You've seen the recording. You try to find each
vocalization and extract them.
Vocalization can be really noisy.
"The world of
silence," says Jacques Cousteau, "really not exist."
A boat
is our enemies in recording. Very
noisy boat.
I preserve you to hear that.
The other way,
neuronal approach
will be a great candidate.
In fact, neuronal, we can't
explain how to classify. But for detection, we
don't care how to find a vocalization.
We just need the vocalization, and we just need
to
preserve whole time. So neuronal approach for only
detection can be a great approach, and it's a work in progress
actually to implement the neural approach
for automatic event detection.
In fact, the manual detection
permit to have some known case,
and
this case permit after to create
all the...
What's my word?
The base dataset or the
model we need ICABS to perform.
The second part,
when we find all
the vocalization, maybe we can lose to some few vocalization,
it's not a problem.
We try to characterize each one.
A characterization,
the description
begin by
acoustics description.
In these two dyes, we have 45 acoustics descriptor,
in temporal information, spectral and
frequency information, and cepstral domain.
Cepstral is the redundancy of the frequency.
And we keep all the contextual metadata.
For example, a recording made in the Gulf
of Mexico or Gulf of America, depends,
are not the same species than a recording doing in Antarctica.
It's really important to
us to know where is the recording. Also,
who did the recording.
People don't work in same species, especially
in bioacoustic, in cetacean,
all neuronal are specialized in one species.
So you use all the
acoustic descriptor and all the data
to describe and to characterize the vocalization.
Can permit a representation of the vocalization.
Each acoustic events, it's composed by all the
descriptor, all the metadata,
the source recording, and all information we can have.
And if they are annotated by an expert,
the expert annotation.
We have a lot of problem with expert annotation because as I say, there are no
consensus,
and it's one part of the end
of this work,
to permit to create a consensus or to describe that.
And the last part of this framework, it's
the classify part.
For this part, we use iKBS, as I say.
We permit to
classify each vocalization,
and extract some knowledge. It's no more information.
It becomes to knowledge, the type of vocalization,
even the species if you know, the individuals.
It's one of the ambition we have. It's to go to
the individual
separation
and many information we need to use,
and we need to
study.
As I say, for whales, for example,
if we can
characterize the vocalization, we can see how they evolve in
time, how they evolve by population geographically.
Whales are two population, distinct two population,
north
and pack whale and south and pack whale. They never meet.
They never cross the equator.
So maybe sometime they will be two species.
They have a lot of influence, a lot of
educational way
with the...
But
I...
And
to be used, iKBS need, as I say, descriptive
model composed by knowing case,
already described, already annotated,
will become a
knowledge base.
For example, you can see here a dolphin
vocalization,
will be classed by acoustics
domain.
And
this, yes, in the 1966,
will be very long time ago. And all the
descriptors report on each domain, and
all the information you need
to
characterize.
To validate this pipeline,
we try to do
proof of concept, and for that, we try to classify
a database, Whactil marine sound database, was commonly used in
neural networks training, so we can compare our
results with them.
There are just a mistake. It's not 67 acoustics descriptor,
it's 45. We
keep some of them because the other are too anthropics
and
not really pertinent to us today.
Covers
seven cetacean species we can see in Reunion
Island
and more than 500
events.
The events are classified into three
acoustics domain: harmonics, impulsive, and stationary,
or combination of this
acoustics domain.
And with that, we have a
great result,
for our first try,
with more than 19% of
accuracy.
The overall accuracy, it's because we have two metrics.
One, it measure if we have exactly the right answer or if
we have just the domain and not the other one.
But it's really interesting because-
It seems to work in acoustics domain.
And the next step, it's to
classify the type of vocalization.
We focus on the type of vocalization for just one reason.
Each species have a lot of vocalization.
Each vocalization corresponds to one species,
even one individual for dolphin.
So it's more interesting to focus on the vocalization.
To go back to TEDx and why this presentation,
it permit to
classify, to describe, and to use the taxonomic way
on
cetacean vocalization.
From the raw recording,
we have
structured observation,
complete by
expert knowledge.
And all of that permit to create AI workflow
in the next step of this one.
And this
characterization
can be resolved,
permit to compare the observation, permit to
see the evolution of time, evolution of geography, as I
say,
and can be adapt
to
large scale AI analysis in future works.
And this resume, as I say, the future works prepare to
AI,
generalized, and a lot of data. We have a lot of PAM
acoustic data. And I hope permit to create an ontology
of cetacean vocalization,
can be proposed to the international community, can be a
consensus, I hope.
Maybe. There's no way to touch.
If you have questions...
So any question?
Okay. So this neural network that you have for classifying sounds in
the first step, are you training this model from scratch, or are you using
some available models?
The neural networks for detection.
For the classification, it's symbolic, it's not neural networks.
But for detection, it's a neural, yes. It's a work in progress.
Actually, I have two internship working on that with me.
It's really
work in progress.
The approach we use,
it's
to use which is already exist. As I say, it's lot of
people working,
and develop
some neural approach,
but dedicate to one species. And we try to
make a multi-agent who
interroges,
questioning all neural networks, all different, to find which
corresponds.
It's a way to know how to
develop all the thing.
It might be a good idea then to consider retraining Birdnet to do what you need to
do, because I assume you did not consider Birdnet because it's typically for birds.
But what it offers is a
skeleton of already existing big neural network for recognizing sounds.
And they have this thing when you can just train features, so you can, with a very
small number of samples from your target species, you can train Birdnet
to do your classification. So maybe that's something that would
streamline your work a little bit if you look into it.
We didn't choose Birdnet because
lot of
difficulty to adapt to underwater acoustics.
Okay.
We have some kind of
event can be adapt.
And all data, working data, are very
heterogeneous
in sampling, in quality.
So Birdnet
need a lot of work to adapt, and we haven't this time.
My PhD finish in few months, so
need to be focused.
The data for the
individual identification, because you mentioned that you might
be able to recognize individuals.
Do you have good data on that?
Could you track them, stuff like that?
We didn't have actually the data and the answer
for the individual. Some studies,
especially in dolphin,
permit to have the hypothesis of their name and use
that.
It's a way to validate this hypothesis.
For whales, we know each one have its one voices,
but we don't know how to describe and how to
separate the voices of whales,
when I talk about right and back right.
But in fact, it's work in progress.
As I say, the POC is only on acoustics domain, so we didn't
become to the individual. It's
hoping result,
but...
Thanks.
Any other questions?
We've got a question online.
So do you think interesting to define a TEDx exchange
format for acoustic data?
And I think it's larger than just for you.
It can be a good way, yes, to
try to make a consensus on acoustic data.
It's a
domain
not really explored actually in TadWIC.
Okay, so I have something to add on this very topic here, because there is
exploration of this topic in TadWIC.
Okay.
It's at the very
beginning phase, but we are doing this.
So there is this thing called Camtrap DP data standard that was
first developed for traditional camera trap data, but there has been project,
it was financed by WildLab, it was called Safe and Sound.
That's the bioacoustic community evaluated whether or not this standard is
good for their needs. And it turned out that yes, it is, because the structure of
data is very similar. You have a stationary sensor, it records some signal, you
recognize some species. So the structure of this data is very similar.
So we are now working on adapting the Camtrap DP data standard to
better fit bioacoustic data. If somebody's interested in this, we have a Camtrap DP
launch at 12:00, so come find us. Yes, please do.
And we're going to talk about this more.
And there is a project financed by NLB called Safer and Sounder to continue the
Safe and Sound project. It's not that creative, but we had to write it very fast.
So
the project starts this December, and the goal is to incorporate the feedback from
the previous project into Camtrap DP standard.
So I think in about a year, there will be a standard under TadWIC
that is ready for bioacoustic data.
So if you work with bioacoustic data, look out for that because we are working on
it, and
we are trying to make this data
enter the interoperable data universe as well.
So it is happening. Keep your eye on that. Thanks.
Yeah.
Maybe we can
be careful to have a link between your works and the SDD,
and not have two separate things.
So yeah. Anything else? Or coffee break?
Nothing online more? Nothing in the room?
Okay, so it was a great session, I think.
Have a good coffee or tea,
and see you around.
Doch, ganz
kurz
dann nur.
Okay.
Hello everyone.
Welcome to the
session today on designing institutional data
science centers for biodiversity.
We have five interesting talks on this topic, and we start
with Lars Voigt. You have 15 minutes
for the talk.
Thank you, and hello everyone. My name is Lars Voigt.
I'm from the Leibniz Institute for the Analysis of Biodiversity
Change. I'm happy to introduce to you the
ideas we have for the LIB Open Knowledge Space.
So this is a conceptual framework for a planned infrastructure
that is key to LIB's Natural Future Museum strategy,
and it's also the core infrastructure that we develop
within the newly created Center for
Biodiversity Knowledge Science at LIB.
So what's the problem? We all know that within museum
collections, there's a lot of information that is relevant for those
people who do biodiversity research, but there's an
interoperability barrier.
So collections are in risk to remain isolated
archives,
and the ideas are out there how to change that.
Everyone's talking about fair principles.
We know how to implement them using URIs, using
ontology terms, schemata, SPARQL, and so on.
But we also know that fairness is not a Boolean property of a
dataset,
but it's basically a continuum within a dataset
is positioned.
And many people say they make their data fair, but what
they actually do is they make the metadata for the datasets fair,
so they build fair containers, but not fair content.
And we believe that we have to build fair content and not only fair
containers.
But unfortunately, producing fair content is really hard
and takes a lot of effort and is also sometimes challenging.
And that's where
our ideas come from for building the LIB Open Knowledge Space.
So the idea is really to have
infrastructure where you can add content
that is immediately usable, fair, and clear to a certain
extent,
and then these representations can be subsequently, in an
incremental manner, be semantically formalized over time
wherever there is need to do that.
And that will be the backbone for LIB's living and evolving
memory.
So how does that work?
We use two ideas or two concepts here.
First, the semantic units framework, where every
piece of
semantically meaningful meaning to a human user
is an addressable unit in that space.
And the other idea is we do progressive formalization,
so content does not have to be formalized
to be added to the stack.
And we will use a running example here in the presentation
Of a beetle that has been observed to feed on
carrion in the morning before it was collected.
So what's the semantic units framework?
The basic idea, and I have that set now, that's the third time
I presented here at TWIC.
It's semantic content, however that is modeled for now,
and that is meaningful to a human user and
represented by its own identifier, its own
resource, that then instantiates a certain type so
that we know what type of information
that is, the semantic content.
And here is a very, very simple example of a text snippet.
So we have our statement up here, the running example,
and here is an implementation that uses OWL,
RDF knowledge
graph. And we link basically the content through
a data property to the resource, as you can see
here.
So low barrier entry, no formalization cost
to do that. And then since it's a semantic unit, we have the
identifier that instantiates a certain class that can
be done with an LLM.
Then we say this content is not
modeled using a logical framework like description logics
or something like that.
We can add metadata, so in case provenance and
technical metadata, and in case the
statement comes from a specific document, a publication,
we can reference that as well, and the extraction method that has been
used.
And then, sorry,
then we create vector embeddings for the content and
link them as well to the resource of that semantic
unit so that we support similarity-based search
and AI-assisted exploration that can then be complemented
with facets if you want to.
The next step is basically take such a text
snippet unit and do entity recognition and
entity linking using Wikidata or ontology terms.
So to semantically enrich the content,
that would give basic semantic search capabilities
on top of the similarity-based search.
The next step is using what we call Rosetta statements.
And Rosetta statements is based on
something from linguistics. Linguists tell us that every
natural language statement, on the top right you can see one,
is organized according to a so-called syntax tree, where every
position, which is a subject, a predicate, or an object, is
assigned in that syntax tree,
and associated with it comes a semantic role within
that tree.
And we can use that here as well with our statement.
We identify the positions, like the subject, and then
we first classify it. So instead of beetle specimen
X123, it is beetle specimen from a certain
ontology.
And then we can go up the taxonomy of the ontology to the
point where it still makes sense for this type of statement.
And in this case, that would be organism. So we generalize that.
And if we do that with every position, we
create what we call a formalized statement,
which is still natural language-based.
Now we take that formalized statement, you see that here on C,
and we create an RDF representation of that
using RDF reification. But instead of just for one
object, we do that for as many objects that the statement has.
So we see the eats, the predicate defines
the class.
That's an eating class, statement class.
Then we have our identifier for that specific
statement, and we link to that the subject and the different
objects. Done.
And since it's a semantic unit, we still have the metadata,
whether
a logical framework has been used and so on.
And we can also create a vector embedding because we can always
use the information from that specific
sentence, put that into our formalized statement, so
we render the content in natural language, and then
apply the vector method on that. So we create a
vector embedding for that as well.
And we can link it back to the text snippet.
So we have the entire trace back again, where
all the bibliographic metadata lies and so on.
So creating some Rosetta statement types
is easy. It takes a little bit of training, like a day of training, and
then you can create your own, so low-barrier modeling.
And since it's an RDF, we have SPARQL
that we can use to query it.
And we can create SHACL shapes for the statement types and do
validation over it.
The next step is, of course, OWL-based modeling.
So we can take
a Rosetta schema, we can create a
semantic model for that type of statement and
schema crosswalk, and then import the data from Rosetta statements
to an OWL-based model.
Where we have highest fairness that we can think of, at least
within the RDF and
knowledge graph world, and we have fair content that we would
build.
But the approach is also technology agnostic, so
the same content could be modeled in a table.
The same applies to the Rosetta statement.
It could be modeled in a table, so it's really technology agnostic.
You can have a stack that's built on RDF Owl or on a property graph
or relational systems.
And we always have the formalized statement as an anchor
that we can use to create vector embeddings for the semantic units
that
is always human interpretable, but still
machine interpretable as well, looking at the
background structure of the Owl
context.
And it is clear compliant because we use
the
formalized statement as a dynamic label to render the
content in the user interface.
And it is LLM friendly because LLMs are
good in processing natural language representations.
There's much more I could tell you about the semantic units framework,
but we don't have the time for that, so I continue with the second part.
That's the semantic letter approach.
So you see here we have-- you can maybe
recognize the text snippet unit, the enriched text snippets unit,
the Rosetta statements, Owl-based representations, and of course,
you could do the same also with higher order logics-based
representations if you need them.
What we will do at LIB is we are currently setting
up a rack-based chatbot to access
our
textual documents at LIB,
and we will develop
a script so that users of that chatbot, we call it
LIB Tell Me,
can, if they identify answers that are relevant to their
research, put that into the space as a
text snippet unit with the link to the
documents from which the answer came from.
And then we have an approach where you can
immediately add natural language
content to the graph and do the semantic modeling, formal
modeling later if you want to.
And you see here where the typical Owl-based knowledge graphs would
rest and on which level or rank.
And we have the diversity workbench where we have structured data of our
collections,
and we will develop semantic models to import that
to this level within the knowledge space.
So you see we have different levels of formalization
that are also different levels of possible interaction
for different communities with the knowledge space.
It supports living and evolving knowledge,
and since every semantic unit is also versioned, it will
always be citable and referenceable.
Alongside the letter, we have a vector layer
because of that formalized statements.
Every statement unit has a vector embedding,
so we can do similarity-based search on that.
And then as soon as we have RDF representations, we can
complement that with Sparkle
search capabilities. And of course, in the higher ranks, we also have
reasoning capability.
Each rank adds fairness and AI readiness, and we can
decide when to push up content
through the levels and through the semi- parametrical
fairness levels.
Most knowledge doesn't need that, so we would do that
whenever we have a use case where we really need that
formalized representations. It's traceable back
to the original text.
Yeah, the conclusion is basically we are here developing a whole
architecture that is based on three principles.
I haven't touched upon the care principles.
We have some ideas on that and intend to develop that
further.
Everything will be open source, and we are open for
collaboration.
And of course, we also want to be
in sync with standards that are developed
and interoperable with standards that are developed in the community.
So
this will become, hopefully, a living and evolving biodiversity
memory for the entire community. We're also thinking of federated
approaches
that
supports progressive formalization that is fair and clear from
the beginning, and that has the full backing of
LIB.
And that's it. Thank you for your attention.
Great. Thank you, Lars. We have a long minute for short
questions. Are there any?
Otherwise, we have some time in the end of the session to have
a more generalized discussion.
So Patricia, please. Next talk is a
little more different. It focuses on the curriculum that might
be necessary to build up structures like that.
Stage is yours.
Thank you.
Good day, everybody. I will present
a collective work with the colleagues from the project
TETRIS and from
the people in TEDx involved in trainings
about what we find out about the need to strengthen taxonomic
capacities and biodiversity information
in education.
So has this ever occurred to you?
It happened to me a lot when in my career I presented
myself
either working in taxonomy or in biodiversity information.
Many
have a bit strange reaction about
taxonomy and nomenclature,
like finding it outdated and dusty.
This is changing a bit over the years, coming out with
all the IT and AI and more presentation, but
still, many people from outside our domain still see
us like that. And even in our domain, many students tell
me, "No, I saw it a bit at school, at university,
but it has tons of rules and Latin names, and
that's something which is not so appealing for me." While when
I'm speaking about biodiversity information, outside our
community, incredible high number of
expert have never heard of it, or they confuse it with
molecular bioinformatics.
And within the TETRIS project that finished
this year, they put the
motto, "Name it to save it."
So we also discuss it. Will really
recognizing being able to name a species
really help to conservation? So I looked a bit up.
You can find tons of references online that shows
that many people from the general public, but also from
biodiversity and biology students, are
unable to recognize their own local very common
species. So I took two striking
examples, like for example, in UK, where only
14% of the students from
level A biology students could
not name more than three common native plants.
And another study from Germany showed that university
students,
more than 80% could only recognize less than 3 of
32 common plants of their country.
I, myself, I like a lot eNaturalist
and
AIs because I can travel the world, I can recognize,
I can find what it is, and I don't get my mother
telling me, "Why did we pay 10 years of studies to
you and you can't even tell me what is this plant?"
But on the other hand,
it's also making us very dependent from technology.
And let's say there is a problem, no more battery, the
network is off. We can be lost in the woods and not
knowing, can we eat this plant or not, what it is.
So it makes us also very dependent, and many become
unable to identify even common species without
having their phone with them.
So now what about taxonomy and nomenclature in formal
university courses? During the TETRIS project, we
identified that actually the subjects are
still often there, but they are hidden somewhere, and they
have disappeared from the titles and even the description of the
courses. Because what I said in the beginning, they sort of have
this feeling
that the students are a bit scared when they read these
terms and then would choose other courses, especially if they are
optional courses.
So
we want also to bring this back, and we hope
that taxonomy courses can dare to have them again
in universities
as becoming part of the main subject and not
just something that is studied by the way, one or two hours
within a larger course on other topics.
And we also identified that many
universities offer fieldwork because it's becoming too
expensive or they have not enough time as
optional activities. Sometimes you
get credits, sometimes not, and actually it's
more that many biologists come out of their
courses without having done any fieldwork during their
curricula.
So during TETRIS, we created a MoU that
six partners signed to really agree to
work together on fostering taxonomic and
biodiversity information trainings, both in
academic trainings at universities, but also
in non-academic trainings and capacity building.
And we are very happy to say that the adventure will continue with
the next project that is called TETRIXX for TETRIS Next Level
that started this September and will go until 2030.
I have some brochure and stickers here that you can take with you to have
more information. And we want to have the ambition to
develop the TETRIXX Academy, to have also an official
European certification system for taxonomic training,
pilots for taxonomic for the future initiative,
including not only classical taxonomy, but also all the modern
tools and AI.
Designing training courses that really cover the whole
spectrum, from field work to species classification.
And we were also advised to have science policy training
from the taxonomic community so that the
funding bodies and the governments also support us more.
Now, what about biodiversity informatics?
Here we notice that there is a real risk of knowledge
transfer. As we know, TDWG exists since the mid-'80s.
As you saw, GBIF is celebrating its 25 years.
Yet, if you look it up, biodiversity informatics
is very rarely a topic or a master
in universities. As a striking example was the
master that was given at the Sorbonne University
together with the Museum of Natural History,
by Régine Vigne, who gave presentations in the previous
sessions. And also Eli Saliba here in the room was part
of this course. But when she retired and Eli find
another job, this course disappeared and is not continued,
which is really sad.
And also we identified that many
experts in the domain have a diploma of biologist of
bioengineers, but they specialized on the job and
they got passionate about it. But very few had actually
really a formal training except from trainings and
workshop where they learned biodiversity by learning from the
community and by themselves.
So what about biodiversity informatics and molecular
bioinformation? So these two disciplines over the years came
much closer. When I started my career, I felt
really a mistrust even between these two communities
because some molecular biologists claimed,
and some do it still now but it's less, that they could
get rid completely of classical and morphologic taxonomy and
that
everything with genetics could replace and make it much
easier to identify species and that we won't
need people to make it a classical way.
And then for a long time when we were collaborating, it
was very much limited that we wanted the voucher
specimens in the museums being kept and
linked to
the data about the sequences that were in the molecular
databases so that there is somehow a proof and a voucher
specimens that can confirm the genetic
identification. And it was not always easy to convince
everyone to really keep the specimen and to
add this information, but that was done.
And now in the past few decades, especially with the development of
barcoding and especially eDNA for biomonitoring,
there are even now TDWG standards on eDNA and
biogenomics and things have become much better
between the two communities and we have genuine very good
collaborations and standards and also joint trainings.
So what about AI? I'm in a project where we did an
inventory of AI courses out there, and
we found out that many university, much faster than in our
domain, are now
setting up in a few years masters in AI.
They are popping up everywhere in all universities.
And I think when we saw all the presentations today and
how AI has become important for our disciplines, this is
certainly a door for us to also get into this
university curricula and also get more funding,
by putting forwards our AI capacities.
And also as we saw in several presentations, TDWG standards are very
important for the part on making the data AI-ready
because they need to be in a certain formal standard.
And we can also use AI to maybe generate
the data directly in TDWG standards, which should also
be quite interesting matter for this biodiversity
information modern curricula.
So what next? If you have seen on the website, we used to have a
TDWG Biodiversity Informatics Curricula Interest Group that has
been dormant for
some time. So we would really like to find people
interested to go into that
interest group again and revive it so that we could do an
inventory of existing formal and informal
training in biodiversity information,
helping to safeguarding the knowledge that is still out
there and securing maybe the archives of training materials
before it may disappear.
That we could also maybe guarantee the knowledge transfer of
the older generation of experts. I'm very happy to see that
many retired people still love TDWG so much that they are around.
I hope I can do that too when I get older.
But I think it's also our duty
to be some of mentors for the younger generation and be
sure that what we acquired as knowledge and lessons
learned can be transferred to them and I see that also as a very
important point for this group.
And then we can also, for the trainings, define
advice and so on, on curricula content
for the different audiences.
I already looked into it. We could collaborate with Alexia
and schema.org, for example, because I'm not a fan of
reinventing the wheel. We already have collaborations with them
via bioschema.org
and also with this EA project. They showed us that they have a
quite nice standards, course instances and
course.
In Schema.org that they developed, that we thought to reuse for
that project, and I hope we can also reuse
it within Tetrix and
Tedrix so that we can align here nicely.
So this is more to catalog the courses and about
metadata. And additionally to that, we might also need
standards to characterize, of course, in a standard way,
more down to the content.
So now to finish, I would like to thank all the colleagues from
the different initiatives that helped me to make this
presentation and were inspirational.
And to finish, I would like to cite Hans van Dijk, who is a
professor in ecology at Université catholique de Louvain,
and he made us a presentation about his recent
publication on cognitive value of studying
nature from childhood wonder to sensory and
cognitive development. And one of his main outcomes is
that we taxonomists and naturalists are mammals that never
left their exploring and play phase and remain
lifelong curious children. So thank you for your attention.
Thanks a lot. I love this one.
We have lots of time for lots of questions if there are any.
Yeah. Tarek, please. Yeah. Do we have a microphone? I don't. Jonas.
Step down again.
Test. Oh, yeah.
This is your stage.
So I've come to know a couple of ecology students over the years,
and what they report most--
I don't know what the question at the end of this will be, but-
Yeah
... what they report most is that they are really bored
by the classical classes on identification
because they don't see a reason in learning how to use these
old identification books and
all of the struggle involved with that.
Mm-hmm.
When in their pockets, on their phone, they have a bunch of
apps. You can take pictures. You can identify birds via sound, stuff like
that. So
what they've told me a lot is they would be interested in
more up-to-date content for the lectures.
But the way it works currently, they're just not willing
to engage with it.
Yes. Well-
Because they-- Yeah
... that's the goal of the Tetrix project and others to,
with this taxonomic for the future,
to try to make it a bit more appealing.
And we have also organized
training courses
with cascading funding. So there will also be, again, calls
within this project to propose these kind of trainings with a bit
of funding. So there, we really made effort to make it more appealing
and combining
modern taxonomy and tools. But for
example, we had a citizen science course with
iNaturalist and other tools,
but there we had specialists
with us
who really showed them how to not trust 100% this tool and
have a bit of critical mind.
And via this way, showing them that these tools cannot
solve everything, and that there are also species that are
so lookalike, so small, or where you need to
identify parts in lab that cannot be identified with a
picture alone.
And also that you need sometimes molecular tools to be sure.
So to show them the whole spectrum, and then make
them understand that being able to identify at
least the basics
up to the family.
Even when I studied at my time, when we hadn't IT tools, we were
asked to be at least able to identify up to the
family. And then it was a bonus if we could identify
genus species,
but we could pass, so that thing is a good way to make it.
Yeah. Thanks a lot. Unfortunately, time is up.
Matt, keep your question for the end.
Yeah.
I will be around.
Thank you, Patricia.
And if you want, I have brochures.
Yeah. So next one,
unfortunately, try to find the mouse.
Here it is.
Is virtually present.
Yeah.
It's becoming increasingly complex, and that raises some challenges
around how we make it interoperable and queryable.
This presentation is driven by three questions.
How do we query biodiversity data in a fair manner?
How do we build a collective knowledge graph?
And how do we do this without straying from known standards?
Over the years, there's been a growing need for a more
complex schema to describe more complex
biodiversity data. This has led to the development
of the now ratified Darwin Core data package.
It is a fully relational format that solves Darwin Core
Archives' conflation problem, wherein information about several
different entities was represented in a single table.
However, amongst its potential issues are the
implicit semantics that are only expressed through table joins
and the fact that such data is difficult to expose online
to data consumers.
The overarching model of the Darwin Core data package is the Darwin
Core conceptual model. It is a model that describes what
entities can be considered and how these entities interrelate.
However, as can be seen in this picture,
it does not use a particular ontology,
relying instead on natural language term
to define the relationships.
An ontology consists of a controlled set of terms,
but it is also an explicit specification of a
conceptualization. Essentially, this means formally
defining the concepts in a particular domain of discourse,
in this case, biodiversity, and how they relate to one another.
This can be expressed using OWL constructs, which
include classes, data type properties, and object
properties, all of which allow for formal
machine-readable semantics.
This lets us conceptualize datasets not only as
tables and rows, but also as a graph
of
nodes and directed edges. In this case, you can
see the portion of data associated with a material
entity of an Antarctic lanternfish.
In this case, the material entity serves as evidence for an
occurrence which happened during an event, which followed a
particular protocol at a particular spatial location.
Everything is connected semantically,
and the model can even be expanded in order to take into account
the media about the specimen itself.
Semantic technologies are powerful because they make meaning
explicit by relying on a set of
well-defined terms. This is done through the use of ontologies,
vocabularies, but also a semantically
explicit query language, SPARQL,
which allows the querying of particular portions
of data. Here on the right, you can see a SPARQL query,
which
requests only the scientific names of Darwin Core
occurrences that happened during Darwin Core events that had
a specific event ID.
And all of the data is exposed through a single endpoint,
which greatly facilitates data querying.
However,
these advantages come at a certain cost.
First and foremost, there is data duplication,
as the data must now exist in
tabular and graph forms.
Second is query frailty. Even if you could query all
endpoints,
service classes can be frail, and it can break.
Third is the technical burden. The entire RDF stack and a
strong ETL pipeline would need to be imposed onto providers.
And finally, schema drift, as there is no guarantee that the
information contained in the graph would match
the information that is contained in Darwin Core data packages.
To address these issues, we have developed the Semantic Data
Cloud, which is a containerized application that
allows for the semantic querying of remote datasets
using semantics based on the Darwin Core conceptual model.
Its core principle is based on the fact that it is the data that should be
distributed and not the infrastructure.
The data should be distributed in the form of exploded
cloud-hosted Parquet files, which rather than being contained in
CSV files in a zipped archive, should be hosted on the
cloud or object storage.
Consider,
as described, Parquet files describing the tables in a Darwin Core
data package being hosted on object storage,
along with an EML JSON-LD file. The user,
seen on the bottom left, can submit a query to the application,
along with optional spatial, temporal,
license, or maintenance-based filters.
Based on these filters, the application can determine
which datasets to consider, but also which to ignore.
Following this, the application
will also
query the JSON-LD files assets
object, which contains hrefs pointing
to the locations of the Parquet files.
In other words, the JSON-LD file
contains no data,
only pointing to the locations of these files, as is seen
in stack catalogs, which are employed in geospatial data.
The application then considers the query, which is a SPARQL query,
and rather than executing it directly, it hands it over to another
application on top, which translates the query from
SPARQL onto SQL.
To do this, the application has a built-in
ontology which considers information about
all the entities in the domain of discourse.
On the top, you would see the information associated with a Darwin Core
event.
And on the bottom, it also contains OBDA
mappings showing how a concept like a Darwin Core
event maps onto
SQL and which columns of which table
to use to rewrite that query.
Since it is
an ontology, it is not just any ontology.
Actually, it
is a particular ontology that satisfies the
OWL2QL profile of OWL2.
This means that it is a little bit less expressive than other
ontologies. However, it is a great fit for
vocabularies like Darwin Core And first and foremost,
this guarantees the translation from a SPARQL
query onto an SQL query. And nevertheless,
expressivity can be recovered where needed.
As it is an SQL query, it can be executed by any SQL
engine. In our case, we consider DuckDB, a fast
analytical engine with a strong affinity for Parquet file.
It can execute SQL queries on the cloud-hosted Parquet
files over HTTP.
After execution, the results are returned to the user.
The query ran against a virtual knowledge graph that
existed only for the duration of the query.
The application keeps a clear separation of technologies,
each playing a distinct role.
A data storage layer by Parquet files, a data discovery
layer by a metadata catalog, a query execution
layer by DuckDB remote SQL, and finally, a
query planning and reasoning layer, which is handled by
SPARQL and an OWL ontology.
In addition,
the SPARQL endpoint is also described using the Model Context Protocol,
or MCP, allowing agentic use of the endpoint.
This way, LLMs can interact with the endpoint,
write SPARQL queries, but also execute them against the SPARQL
endpoint.
There is currently a live instance of the application
hosted at data.qcbs.ca. It contains all
the described services, such as the SPARQL endpoint, the
metadata catalog, as well as the MCP server.
It contains over 50 real data sets that were downloaded
from GBIF and mapped onto the Darwin Core data package format.
All source code is freely available on GitHub, and you can access it
by scanning the associated QR code.
Thank you very much for your attention.
Okay. Thank you for this one. Unfortunately, he's
not here, so we can't have any questions.
I ask Tarek to enter the stage.
For the online community, whoever is watching, under Home,
Questions and Answers from the Audience, you can ask questions
and I put them in here.
Yeah. This one here goes.
Oh, this works. Okay. Hi.
My name is Tarek. I'm a PhD student in Leipzig,
Jena.
I work mostly at IDIV and formerly at the uni in Jena.
And today, I'm really excited because we're going to talk about
an actual prototype of a lot of the ideas that Lazars introduced today,
or earlier this week as well.
And for the running example for today, we're going to look at the Phenops
database. If you've been at the presentations
yesterday for the
phenological database, for example, Phenops is included there as well.
We have a global
set of botanical gardens that people go to every
week and observe phenological traits of the plants inside of the
gardens. And this is going to be
our starting example, a use case we're going to see pretty often,
right? So you have your data set as a CSV file,
or in this case, an Excel sheet, and you want to model
a pretty simple statement, right? You have a plant.
You want to
say something about its growing season length. That's kind of the trait.
But then actually, what the end goal would be to have this knowledge
graph
representation in RDF,
the jump from B to C is a bit problematic, right?
There's a lot more involved in that
than it may seem. So
the questions we're asking today is how can we simplify the
integration of semantic models and knowledge graphs,
and simplify knowledge graph construction?
But then also, how can we leverage these
advanced semantic models
for more fair, more clear, and AI-ready knowledge graphs?
And
that
leads us to
needing knowledge graph constructions for both
machine but also human actionable data.
And
I'm just going to give a quick intro again to Rosetta statements and
semantic units. Lazars thankfully already explained something
about this today. But starting with Rosetta statements,
they're basically formalized natural language statements, so we're going to walk
through this example. We have the same statement as in
the introductory example. And
when we,
in step B, abstract away from that and formalize it a little bit more, right?
We can see that a statement like the one above, that we
could switch out different traits for, could switch out different subjects for,
it has specific syntactic positions that make up the statements, but also
different semantic roles. So
at the very beginning, we have this subject.
The subject has some kind of quality, and then the other two slots at the
back,
they tell us something about that quality.
And when we fill these semantic roles a bit more,
then we can decide, well, the subjects, usually when we want to make
this kind of measurement, they're probably material entities, right?
These properties are usually what we
would refer to as qualities and in kind of a path.
So the slots that make up the statement, be they
required or optional.
And
so for Rosetta statements, a
couple of takeaways. We have a meta model for statements.
We have a way of passing
statements or input data to get to these statements, and
we can use them as a bridge to easier knowledge graph construction and
usage, or at least that's the goal.
And then for semantic units,
as Rosetta statements, they focus on single statements and how
to express them. Semantic units are
a bit more concerned with
structuring statements and how different statements relate to each other.
So
what we want to do is we want to give an
identifier to a statement,
so that we can have collections of triples and
treat them as units of meaning. So what are collections of triples talking about?
Formalize different types of these statements, and then therefore
reorganize or put some structure on top of formal knowledge graphs
that
introduce layers of abstraction,
different representational granularity.
And for an example here, so this is the same
example again, a semantic unit put on top of this
would look like this. So we have
our semantic content in the blue box at the top that
contains our original triples. But
we've now introduced this growing season length statement unit
with a specific class that tells us what this type of semantic
unit is all about.
We can attach metadata, as Lazarus talked about,
and we now have a way to reference this set of triples here at the
top
by just
referencing this single
resource in the knowledge graph. And what I want to present
today is how we can combine the two.
So
at the top, C, you have this
Rosetta statement we just had. Here in D, we have the
specific example of the statement unit and how
can we combine the two and get from one to the other?
So how can we use Rosetta statements as an input
for
knowledge graph construction or mapping systems and arrive at this
representation?
And
I put up as is connected to Rosetta statement library that you
can see on the right side. So we have different types of statements.
We can talk about geo-indexing, time information, how
scientific observations are supposed to be modeled, stuff like that.
And I wrote a compiler that takes the inputs
and outputs two things. So valid RML mappings that we can execute to
get to RDF, and also a SHACL path for
validation that
validates the output. And
talking a bit more about the templates,
we
have five different dimensions of information in these
templates. We have definitions of the Rosetta statement type.
So what slots can there be?
Are they optional?
Are they required or not? And then similarly for the semantic
unit, what kind of
information or what kind of structural
properties should the semantic unit have?
Then what kind of RDF pattern is supposed to come out of the compiler?
This you may also know as ontology design patterns if we're talking about single
ontologies.
Then some validation constraints and something that's very interesting for
users, human and machine-readable dynamic labels.
And the
results
are really interesting, I would say.
So on the right side,
I put up an example of how we would fill these mappings.
So that's a YAML representation.
This is what we ask users to fill out,
instead of writing traditional RML or R2RML
mappings. And
turns out this is four times shorter than conventional mappings,
which in the Phenop's example,
means a reduction of, I think, 3,000 mapping lines from 4,000
to 1,000, which is already very incredible.
Then we get these dynamic labels, like the one here at the bottom, when
we combine different types of semantic units.
So we get a whole bunch of information that we might want about a
plant, where it's from, what the growing season length is.
We also have coordinates for where it was spotted.
And
this is
how the final graph might look like for
this example. So at the very bottom, we have the base data
graph. So this is like the traditional knowledge graph that
you would usually arrive at.
And then we have a layer of statement units on top.
We have different kinds of observations for different qualities.
We have the locations, botanical gardens, universities,
time information.
We can then abstract one layer higher to introduce
simple compound units. So we can
compile different flowering traits, fruiting traits, senescence
traits, and group them together,
split them up a bit higher into this
group of vegetative versus reproductive traits.
And then at the very top, we can also introduce this time
series information, how-
do these plans across years.
How do they develop across the years?
And we can also separately query this.
And I think what's worth a discussion here is I've also collected
the number of triples. As you might see,
graph size more than doubles, so
we're going to have to figure out a way
to-- You can't circumvent it, but we're going to have to find out
how much impact
that's going to have on querying and everything.
But
yeah. So
I think with that, we're pretty much... Oh, no, future work. Yeah.
So for future work, this is just one example.
So what we're going to work on next is getting
the pipeline into a first release version.
We can
extend the pipeline to
different other use cases, and we're envisioning it as people
can author their own templates and to be reused by others then.
What is the impact of semantic units on downstream tasks is also a really
interesting
question. For example, how do
LLM-based RAG systems, for example, use these dynamic
labels compared to the traditional
graph schema when retrieving answers?
Yeah. And
for this, yeah, I think we're done.
I wanted to reuse this figure again because I think it looks nice.
Thank you to
everyone who helped working on this, and thanks for listening.
Yeah, and if you have questions.
Thanks a lot. Thanks a lot, Tarek, and thanks a lot for being that much in time
that we have more time for questions here.
Any?
Okay. Yeah, Matt?
Oh, okay, because then you have more time for your talk.
Yeah.
Okay. Good decision.
Where is it? Why is it there?
It's a PDF, isn't it? Okay.
Can you drop it on a browser?
Yeah.
I'm a little bit lost here how to start that one.
Control + L.
Aha. Great. Thank you.
So stage is yours.
All right. Thanks everybody for being here.
It's my great pleasure to give the last talk of TADWIG.
Not really, but
I want to step back and talk a little bit more about the
sociocultural aspect of AI. We've been hearing an
immense amount and a great depth about AI
from the technical perspective, some really wonderful ideas coming from all of
the German group who's working on it.
But I'm not going to talk about the technical part of it.
I'm going to talk about our experience as a center with
AI. So,
what kind of center are we? A little bit of an introduction.
I'm coming from the Species File group.
We're one of the longest running endowed biodiversity informatics
groups that are out there. We've been endowed for about 15
years, and our members in there have been working for as long
as some of the TADWIG old-timers. Not quite, but almost in there, I was
thinking, back to
about 25 years old.
We have around 10 full-time employees, and we have around 100
collaborative projects around the world that we're working on.
And so in this age of AI, we've been tasked to think about how
AI might impact us, and we've also been tasked with
thinking bigger than our group in general by administration.
And so we're thinking about going from group to alliance.
And partly we're thinking about that to see how we might evolve and scale.
We feel fairly strongly that there's very important
aspects of being in a network with respect and risk management that
would benefit. And yeah, distributing risks and
benefits.
And I want to say that the centers that I'm talking about are really collectives of
people.
So I am extremely grateful, and
sitting in bed last night and thinking about our team, it just warms my heart.
Except for Debbie over here.
So everybody knows Debbie Paul, our TADWIG person, and I just want to
double-check something with Debbie.
Is she currently the leader on Whoova, on the most
interactions on the leaderboard?
And I do hope she is. Otherwise, we might have to talk, Debbie,
afterwards. Number two, let's get on it. Okay.
So it is about people. Centers are about people, and we have a wonderful
diverse group of expertise. We have ex-TADWIG leaders.
We have ICZN members. We have people who are responsible for
the infrastructure of the Encyclopedia of Life, et cetera.
I can't go through them all, but it is about the people. That's what a center is.
And so, again, what we're thinking about is rebirth in the time of
AI, and there's an allusion to a very famous book
that uses two other words that I may or may not be alluding to here.
I'll let you try to puzzle that out.
And so I'm just going to go through 10 things about how AI has impacted
our center and our sort of thinking.
And of course, this is outdated before it started because AI, right?
All right. So first, is AI really changing things?
One of the things we can do is look to math, where they have a concrete
system
to prove that AI is right. It's this lean reasoning system.
And so math, if you follow the news, and that field has been impacted by
AI perhaps more than any other field.
And what's come out of it are things like the Leiden Declaration response
that you see here on the left.
And what I find fascinating is that the parts that
are for organizations,
centers,
if you look at all of those things, those are just
good principles for centers.
So what is the role of AI for centers if any center, regardless
of AI, should be following those things?
Only when we come down to policymakers do we see that we should
regulate the artificial intelligence agency. So what does this mean?
It's just kind of an interesting pondering with respect to math.
I think strongly one of our biggest bottlenecks is not compute,
but it's hardware, storage. I want to be able to never say
no when somebody comes to me with data. If I can do that, watch out.
We can fly. All right? So what's typically happening is somebody needs
storage, so we get some, and then we need more storage, so we repeat and we repeat,
and then we need lots of storage. So we go to Amazon, like iNaturalist, and you get
infinite storage. Then we all aggregate our data, and now
aggregated data means something very useful for AI.
Right? And so we build models, but we didn't talk to our community.
And then the community, if you follow what's going on in various places, gets very
mad that you use their data to build an AI model.
So
storage is a very important factor, and I think as a community, we need to figure
out how to get infinite storage to deal with infinite problems.
Standards are more important than ever. We're here at TDWG, right?
And I hear that we don't need standards anymore in our community.
Let's just launch it at AI. Everything works. Let's parse some data.
It'll be easy, right? What should we parse into?
It was then that they knew they needed a standard.
You parse into standards to do things practically, right?
And so you need them both on the front end, like we've heard, and on the back end.
And so standards provide biodiversity information centers a sort of
sea of stability in the wave of AI.
All right.
Broad awareness of the digital world.
We are increasingly seeing
taxonomists, but not only taxonomists, people who we would consider
citizen scientists producing amazing tools.
And so as a center, we have to be aware of those tools to draw
them back in and persist and improve them over time, right?
Experiments are being run at an unprecedented scale.
People are building things that we know we've needed for 30 years, but nobody's had
the chance. Now with large language models, you can.
You can build those applications and those tools.
So we need to see those but harden them, because what they're building is somewhat
fragile with respect to how we think of things over time.
Two things. There's a love-hate relationship.
Administrators all love AI, obviously, right?
But it tends to be more visionary and not practical.
And so there's genuine excitement about really what we can do in our organizations.
And we've been tasked as a center to have to write things like white papers that
address AI. And we've been tasked to think about changing
and to
sort of hit that. But we're already starting to see some pivots in the
administration where, well, maybe this won't quite work over here, and
maybe it'll work over here. So this is really tricky.
And we've also had some acceptance that, well, maybe AI is not going to solve all
our problems. Maybe financial should not be touched by the AI, but you scientists,
you use AI, right? So
it's a little bit there. And the big question is, do biodiversity information
center administrators love it, right?
Many hate AI, and I'm using the word hate as in hate.
Social media hates AI, and you will have to deal with it
if you present stuff.
I'll say that from experience.
Some people, we have to make corporate
partnerships to extend. We need Amazon-level services, or
iNaturalist wouldn't exist. But some people are drawing a strong line.
It's never okay to be a corporate partner.
And fellow researchers face genuine problems.
We have researchers in our institution that we know, love, and trust
who are talking about being journal editors,
and absolutely,
their lives are turned upside down.
They cannot just accept AI at this point because of all of the nature
of publishing in that industry.
So this is a real concern. And so as a center, how are
we going to
invest in even more education of ourselves and the others as to the
nuances of AI's role in our centers?
Walls and silos are inevitable, required, and pointless.
All right. So what I mean here is that you're hearing a lot of talk about
protecting our data. Right?
Creating a purpose for use for our data.
And data on the internet are everywhere by default.
If you put your data up there, it doesn't matter how many passwords,
what kind of protection, what kind of shared authentication, my premise is, is that
it will make its way out there. So for example, if you have protected
species data,
you can't pull that back once it's off the internet. It's there.
And you will get hacked sooner or later.
If banks are being hacked, if medical institutions are being hacked, if the FBI, as
of last week, is apparently being hacked, we as a biodiversity informatics
community do not have those resources to think that we can present
more protection than they can. So let's be more creative, and
let's figure out what's going. And actually, I think this is really important
because I think that-
If we made our data more free, if people in kindergarten knew that we
needed to protect
species in Africa protected areas, then guess what?
If we were taught that, and they knew exactly where those species were from the
get-go,
then we would be forced to protect them.
So let's not pretend to hide protected information.
Let's get it out there. We don't have time not to, is my
little rant there.
AI has impacted at scale. Every biodiversity informatics center that we know
of is using Cloudflare to protect them.
This is the wall between them, personal app, and not. So it's all over.
And so this concept is maybe smaller siloed efforts will shepherd and protect
meaning as we go forward.
So yeah, I think we need to take back, embrace, and reforge the concepts of
silos, walls, and borders as things that serve our work, not as things
that isolate us. And maybe we can ask how do we use AI to accomplish this?
All right. Open science isn't open-ended.
We heard lots of nuances about what fair means, et cetera.
This is the GitHub outage report. So yellow and red is bad there.
So if we put open source code out there, now we have large language models
making pull requests to our open repositories that we have to deal with.
Is this useful or not?
And so, AI noise hitting everything is kind of
inevitable. Our applications, our data, et cetera.
And an arms race requires resources we don't have, like I just said.
So is harnessing more AI the solution?
We love the idea of round-tripping and data at TADWIG
here. But if AI starts round-tripping,
what do we do? Because we're going to get washed out.
All right?
So open has been our mantra. AI requires that
biodiversity information centers spend much more time and energy to
maintain open. And can AI help us to maintain open?
Number nine, embracing the long-term amongst uncertainty.
In the last year and a half, I think we can all agree that nothing is certain.
And it's scary, and
we need to think about a lot of different things. We've had outages.
We've been hacked.
We've seen resources disappear. We're seeing collections close.
We've got politics.
Who knows what we're going to have for breakfast tomorrow?
And AI and its products have this sort of brittle feel to them.
If you spend a lot of time with them, they are quick.
They kind of do some wonderful things, but they sort of feel brittle.
And so that's creating even more uncertainty.
And so,
people, if we can start thinking about how to mitigate our risk
across networks of people, not just in our centers, but across
individuals, maybe citizen scientists, how can we get data out them,
back up to their phones, back up to their infrastructures, back up to their
little mini servers offline, might help risk.
And I think, again, people are the heart of that.
So how do we get people to help
deal with all this uncertainty?
So biodiversity centers are long-term havens for people who use
technology, not technology serviced by people.
And the role of AI is to serve life, is the take home
for our centers.
Last, thank you, Patricia. You nailed it with that wonderful
quote.
Amongst all this uncertainty,
we've had the honor and the privilege to work with many research groups
who are incredibly excited about AI.
I
could do this job and it would take me
two to three months to process one sample, and now I can do it
in two to three hours. And I have thousands of samples to
maybe
annotate a 3D micro CT image coming from a synchrotron.
And I also have genomes for all of these.
And AI is giving me the excitement to connect those dots and the power to connect
those dots.
And so,
when I see a fellow researcher who I know, love, and trust express that
excitement over all of these kind of areas,
that's a lot of
motivation to
work with that group. And I think
when we, as a biodiversity information center,
experience this curiosity and passion, our role,
because we're persisting over time, is to fuel that passion and
curiosity to the best of our degree.
So AI requires
us to figure out new ways to make people more passionate.
Thank you.
Come build with the Species File group or whatever alliance we evolve to.
Come join our virtual conference every May. Look for that.
And we have open community hours, regardless of whether or not you
use our tooling, every Wednesday,
every week, religiously.
So come share your voice. Thanks very much.
Thanks a lot, Matt. Are there specific questions for Matt for his
talk?
Okay, none. Thanks to all the speakers that I don't have
to use this one
all the time. And thanks to that, we have triple
times this one left for discussion.
And
we prepared something.
If there aren't any from the audience,
try to cope with Windows here. It's not that easy.
Ah.
Message from El-Amin. He is online virtually, so if you have
questions regarding his talk,
feel free. It's in the WoA app,
however it's pronounced.
It's not working, but I'm able to read.
So,
we've heard a lot about the
open knowledge space that we are going to build up at LIB.
We've heard from Patricia about
how to align taxonomy biodiversity
informatics, how this is supported by Tetris and the recent
Tetrix project, and the plea
for
reviving the Tetrix interest group on biodiversity
informatics. We've also the other side, how to
access those data using a federated search.
So all the data lying around there
in a semantical way. We have Tarek on the
practical example of the Rosetta statements and the
semantic units framework proposed by Lars.
And last but not least, Matt Yoder on the
AI and what has everything to do with that and his ten
principles engraved in stone. So,
to the audience,
what do you think? What belongs in an institutional
biodiversity knowledge data science center, and what should
instead be provided by a shared federated infrastructure?
So this is the
thing, what
do we keep on our own in our data centers, and what do we
share publicly? And
are there any ideas? We have a lot of audience here, a lot of people from
different institutions.
Any ideas on that? Bjorn is willing to help with the mic.
Sorry, could you clarify?
Are you interested in what we should keep locally in terms of skills and what we
should share in terms of skills? Or what we should keep locally in terms of data?
It's an interesting idea to also keep locally the skills,
but I meant data. Skills, I would
love to have it shared as soon as possible, like Curricula,
for instance.
Yeah. So, there are initiatives to have better
handling of data skills amongst research
organizations,
better recognition of software skills amongst the practitioners
that we work with.
But that's very patchy across different countries.
Yeah.
Thanks.
Lars, on that?
Thank you. So, I think this really depends on
the owners of the data and what they want.
And
for some, it might be good to host it themselves, because then they
have complete control of what goes in and out.
So you can also think of a federated
knowledge space where data providers define--
They don't want to share the data, they want to make it visitable, so
they define the queries that they allow on their dataset.
And they have, with that, complete control.
But others maybe don't have the
money
and the infrastructure and the knowledge to provide
a federated point in that
space. And for those, it's good to have
institutes that offer that as a service to the
community. And besides that, I think the entire
stack, so that makes everything interoperable, the semantic
artifacts, the ontologies, the schemata,
and also maybe certain operations services should
go into the hand of institutions so that we have
long-term sustainability for this.
Yeah. Thank you.
This is somehow what has been started with GBIF. Yeah?
So we have the local nodes that contributes to the
worldwide GBIF dataset, but helps the local
institutions, smaller university collections, to
open up the data.
I think we have to share everything. Like everything, radically.
I'm really glad that Matt ended by talking about the bigger
picture around AI and how it is influencing
our
culture and our world in ways that we can't
predict, and I think we still don't understand.
It is true that a lot of people hate AI,
especially on the left and the upper crust,
and people who talk about these things.
And I'm coming from Canada. If you travel through small-town
Canada, all you will see is AI-generated posters.
People love it. They love AI. They use it every
day for everything.
And so
The large companies, OpenAI, Anthropic,
Google, and anyone riding their coattails, have a vested
interest in people using this stuff as much as possible and it embedding itself
in culture. And,
I don't really want to set up the narrative that those companies are the enemy,
but they are.
They always have been. Large capitalism is what
we're pushing against here.
And so I think we need to unite our resources.
We will never be able to match the amount of compute that industrial
capital can put up, but we can certainly share compute.
We can share tools and resources.
And
if I can pull out my soapbox, people who have concerns about
copyright and privacy and protecting things,
that serves the interests of the big publishers.
It serves the interests of the large corporations.
They love to keep things secret and charge money for them.
So the more we cannot do that,
the better. I think I've said enough controversial things right
now.
But I think it's time for a radical
attitude towards sharing things with each other.
Thank you. Last one, Debbie, on this?
Okay, leave me. Okay.
Yeah, just very quickly to bring it back to part of what Nikki referenced.
I know at our own institution, so you can see,
and I'm thinking about Brazil too.
So I had heard a statistic at some point that only about half the
Brazilians have one of these.
So in the midst of all this, make it open and put it out there and make it
available,
they have access issues. At our own institution, I was able to see the
difference between a working group that's clearly talented, vested,
exploring this new space collectively, and then a whole
group of people who've never even touched it, for fear,
for whatever reason.
And then making a space for that to happen and having 70% of the room say they've
never tried it yet, but walking out of the room going, "Oh my God, I had no
idea how much I could change my research workflow." And then the next question
was, how can you help me do that? And figuring out at our institution how we make
a space for those people so we can have a, for those of you who know the
Carpentries, a day three model where we can help them with their workflows and
help them envision how this can be useful in their space.
Because some of us are happy exploring, other people haven't stepped into the
puddle yet.
And at the same time then, this alliance, so somebody brought
up the GBIF speaker in our
symposium, brought up the notion of, sure, I've got this
working node and it's great, but we have the same
story about how do we keep it going and how do we keep the people vested and how do
we get more people involved, because you do have turnover.
And it's the same thing with the skills.
As fast as you can make these talks and these points, the ground has shifted under
us. So I think there's a lot of potential in an alliance there.
That's it.
Okay, really the last one, okay? Then we have to come up to the next
question.
Okay, then I promise I'll be quick. Sharon at the Field Museum.
To dovetail on Deb and Nikki,
yes, let's get everything open. But we also have to think about who
and where does data come from in the beginning?
Traditional knowledge, indigenous data, governance.
Let's bring the two together, right? Because there are a whole raft of people.
If we're going to empower
us, let's empower them to understand what we're making openly
available on their behalf. So just putting that out there as a thing to remember
as we go down all the make everything open route.
Yeah.
Can I just correct something? Because this statistic is-
Yeah, sure.
The statistics that half of Brazilians don't have a smartphone, I
would like to know where did you get from, because-
Maybe that bag is full.
Yeah, maybe even more than that, because that's far from reality in
Brazil.
Yeah, just to add that. Sorry.
Okay, thanks for the correction.
But in general then, access is an issue for people that don't.
Can I say that actually in Brazil there is a startup that lends smartphones, so
that's a very old idea of
the-
Okay, I have found out that sharing starts with the
ability to know how to plug in USB sticks.
Okay, second
answer. What is currently the biggest obstacle?
Technology, semantic skills, governance, or sustainability
when it comes to those
knowledge spaces we are thinking of and we are dreaming
of? Do you have any ideas on that?
Tarek, please.
Yeah, maybe to give my opinion on this.
This is currently an obstacle, but also I think for when we're talking about
bigger institutions, an opportunity as well.
You need a way to get people to, for example,
researchers in ecology, this is what we encounter a lot, to actually
make their research data available, but also to help them to do that because they
don't know. They don't know what good data quality is.
They don't know how to semantify their data, and so on.
Currently, they're not incentivized to do that on their own, right?
Funding for research runs out, and then they're gone.
So institutions, they
have the power to put structures in place
to
make workflows that work across the institution to get
research data into a state that is open for everyone and
anyone. And also, it's our responsibility,
mostly on the computer science side,
to ... develop systems
that support people in actually doing that, right?
Because
semantifying data is very difficult, we all know that,
and we can't expect people to do that
from scratch, and we really have to help them, and we can.
Okay, thanks. But please point a little bit more to the question here.
So what do you think are the next steps when we do the next step
towards implementing such a knowledge space?
What are the obstacles we should face first, second? Please.
Yeah. Then I'm probably
in the wrong direction going now, because I would like to comment
what was just said, that researchers do not know.
I disagree. I think majority of researchers
know.
But
I think there is some laziness in that because they want to do it fast
just to get rid of it, just to publish it, and the fastest
way is to publish a mess, what you have, an Excel file,
right?
So I think the standards, the clean data,
should be
forced by
papers maybe.
Because if the
journals do not allow you to publish or attach
messy data without the standards, you won't be able to do
that, then you will be reinforced to clean and publish
standardized data.
So sorry, I'm not following the questions.
Yeah, it's fine.
Matt?
So I like that idea a lot, and I would argue that
that's one mechanism of journals.
But the other sort of philosophy that we've had at SFG
is that we are going to build tools,
applications that meet the needs of the researchers.
And hidden underneath that is the semantic layer that
they don't need to see that. And so I think what we're saying is that there's
a big need for those tools, those apps, those things that make born
digital in the field trivial for that researcher.
But behind the scenes,
crazy triples, right?
And
that's honestly how we've approached it.
We've tried to give people interfaces quite literally, or
workflows in an application. But yet, behind the scenes
were those data models and those storages, and those awareness of the
low-level needs,
and that bridges the gap.
I'll also say the biggest obstacle is point to storage.
We need federated storage, all of it.
I would also like to add, it's also up to us as a
community because we are the reviewers then, right?
And if you review something and you look at the data and it's a mess,
you should point that out.
Thank you.
Next question,
leading towards
the last talk. What changes because of AI?
And the most important thing, we all know that that changed a lot.
What
should we start doing now that we would not have considered five
years ago?
So we all fear the threat of AI, of capturing
the knowledge, of
hindering young people to get educated on taxonomy.
So what are the next steps, or would be the most obvious
steps next to do now to
somehow safeguard taxonomy, biodiversity
informatics, data as we
know how to consume them up to now? What has changed, and
what are the next steps, Matt?
I'll echo it again what I tried to bring up.
I think we need small teams of people who are trained to see and
survey the world for those aha moments. Right?
So we actually are going to have to invest in teams of people whose
job is not to build the tool, it's to recognize the tool
and to recognize the impact that a citizen science is making,
or a scientist is making, or that a fellow researcher in a sort of an
obscure journal has posted their AI
innovation because they could create their own app.
So I think we
have to focus on training people to recognize innovation and
things that capture our imagination so that we can bring them back,
and this is a standards body, this is TADWIG, so that we can bring it back and we
can standardize it and make it part of our infrastructure.
Tim, over there.
And I won't go on another anarchist rant, I promise.
I think we should embrace messiness and being messy in public
because
AI is capable of making these very polished outputs, and this is something that the
Journal of Open Source Software recognized in a really good blog post about how
they're evaluating software now.
It's more about the community uptake and that
engagement piece.
And I think often, as academics, we get really caught up in everything has to be
polished and perfect.
But I'm starting to feel like if I saw somebody whose slides were
messy and had maybe some typos and maybe some hand
drawings in them, I might feel good about that because it's something they made
themselves authentically.
So I think that's something we'll start seeing more because of AI and
something we should embrace.
Yeah.
Noah?
So
also seeing the discussions that we had these days,
I also see a gap,
for instance, between people from the US and people from
Europe, where we see in Europe that more institutions
have rules set up not to use, for
instance, big tech AI.
And on the other hand, we see in the US that in academia,
everyone is using that. And if we want to combine forces,
I see a problem there that we have to discuss.
So I know time's up, but
the last question,
it's a take-home message also for us here, and then we ask you to
help. If the institutions represented in this room wanted
their knowledge spaces to interoperate five years from
now,
let's say seven, okay? What is the one thing we need to agree on or
build together first? We know storage.
Other keywords? Nikki?
Thank you. You need to invest in your people.
What?
You need to invest in your people.
Yeah. Sorry, I didn't get it.
Pat?
Well, you need to change also the mentality
of the managers of some institutions, because some of
mine, when somebody leaves, they cut the whole
emails, the whole history, and the person disappears from the website,
while we plea to keep them on, even if they're retired, and to
keep the history of the former employees, which is sometimes
simply "No."
And then also for the content themselves to guarantee
portability, so that when a format
of data become obsolete in the storage,
that there is some kind of screening, that they are transformed
in formats that are still readable
if, for example, they are
getting obsolete. So that is often forgotten, and you
find back archives that are in very old Word or
whatever format that no current software can read easily
anymore.
So archival techniques and tradition of
knowledge. Yeah.
Any more?
Okay, then I think time's really up.
Thanks for the lively discussions and thanks to all
the speakers, also El Amin online, and
I wish you a nice concluding conference, and I guess
we have lunch by now.
Come to the Unconference.
Yeah, and come to the
Unconference.